Guide to the Alumni Class materials, 1823-1998 MS2130
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Alumni Class materials
1823-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2130
23.5 Linear Feet
Collection includes scrapbooks, papers, diplomas, newspapers, textiles, and memorabilia from various sources associated with alumni of the University.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through gifts from alumni and alumnae.
Collection Scope and Content
A collection of scrapbooks, papers, diplomas, newspapers, textiles, and memorabilia from various sources associated with alumni of the University. They range in date from 1823 to 1998.
Collection Organization
Organized in eight series: Images and visual works; Textiles and apparel; Scrapbooks; Personal papers; Diplomas, certificates, awards; Cherry Tree yearbooks; Newspapers, magazines, newsletters; Professional tools.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Choral singing; Medicine; Scrapbooks; Sports; Football; World War, 1939-1945; Students; Washington (D.C.); Buildings; Greek letter societies; Drama; Veterans; George Washington University; Marvin, Cloyd Heck; Eliot, Thomas D. (Thomas Dawes); George Washington University. Law School; Strong, Hattie M.; Wheeler, Woodbury; Needham, Charles Willis; Nordlinger, George; George Washington University--History; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Balfour, Donald C. (Donald Church); Columbian University; Columbian College in the District of Columbia
- Images and visual works, 1860-1972; MS2130 Series 1; 4 Linear feet (Box 26, Box 6, Box 20, Flat box 29, Box 38, Box 31)
  Scope and Contents note
  This collection consists of photographs, including sports teams, campus activities, greek life, and events. They range in date from 1860 to 1972.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    General note
    Four folders in box 3- Accession number 471 Donation from Ann Marie Sneeringer McKay
    Pictures: Dec. 1957- Jan. 1958
    Troubadours Group Shot
    Photos: 1956-1958
    Photos: Jan. 1959
    Ann McKay was a member of The George Washington University Cheerleading Team during the late 1950s. She received her B.A. in Education from GW in 1960. She was also active in the Glee Club, Traveling Troubadours, and Student Council. This note was written in 2005.
  - Francis Strayer football photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    -- Football scenes for newspaper publication, many include names of players --'Tuffy' Leemans, GWU --GWU vs. LA State, 10 Nov., 1934 --Vanderbilt vs. GWU, 3 Nov., 1934 --GWU vs. Shepard, 29 Sept., 1934
    Francis Strayer presented these materials to the university in October of 1993. Strayer was a 1934 graduate of the university, playing both football and baseball for GW. This note was written in 2005.. Materials in the collection include yearbooks, football programs (autographed), photographs, including "Tuffy" Leemans" and a scrapbook of his years at GW. The collection also includes two artifacts, a letterman sweater and a large athletic blanket, presented to Francis Strayer in his senior at the university. Formerly ACC 203.
  - Francis Henry Strayer sport photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Folders 1-3 in box 4
    Gordon Basketball Team photo --1959-1960 Gordon Junior High School Basketball Team, with Coach Strayer --1954-1955 Gordon Basketball Team, with Coach Strayer --1952-1953 Gordon Basketball Team, with Coach Strayer --Athletic photo, 4-22-1959 --Newspaper photo of Coach Strayer's fencing team practicing --Kermit 'Zuzu' Stewart, guard, 1933 --Captain Ed Clark, GWU tackle, 1934 --2 football photos
    Francis Strayer presented these materials to the university in October of 1993. Strayer was a 1934 graduate of the university, playing both football and baseball for GW. This note was written in 2005. Materials in the collection include yearbooks, football programs (autographed), photographs, including "Tuffy" Leemans" and a scrapbook of his years at GW. The collection also includes two artifacts, a letterman sweater and a large athletic blanket, presented to Francis Strayer in his senior at the university. Formerly Acc 203.
  - Francis Strayer football photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    --Coach Strayer --Harry Deming --George Washington vs. LA State, 10 Novt., 1934 --full GWU football team (2) --various football game scenes --Tulsa, 1934
  - Caricature of George Nordlinger, undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
    George Nordlinger (1897-1994) was a member of The George Washington University community for over three quarters of a century, as a student, faculty member and emeritus professor. A life-long Washington, D.C. resident, he was born there April 30, 1897. He graduated from Western High School, and from GW with an A.B. degree in 1918. From the time he was a small boy he wanted to be a doctor, and went on to Medical School at GW, receiving his M.D. in 1922. Three years later, after doing work in hospitals in the U.S., Dublin and Vienna, he returned to begin what would be a thirty-seven year faculty appointment teaching obstetrics and gynecology. He was fondly known as \Uncle George\ to students who took his courses, including the first courses on birth control offered by the School in 1930.
    While on the faculty, Dr. Nordlinger also maintained a private OB/GYN practice, delivering more than 7,500 babies during the course of an active professional life. The Medical School's Class of 1949 dedicated their yearbook to him, noting that he had been "unanimously selected as the Godfather of the Class, in appreciation of the many watchful hours he has spent before and during the delivery of our sons and daughters. We shall always be grateful for his kind assistance as our instructor, obstetrician, and friend."
    Dr. Nordlinger retired from the faculty in 1962, and from private practice in 1969, but remained a frequent visitor to the GW campus, even taking history classes in his late eighties, saying that as an undergraduate and medical student he was so focused on the sciences there was "no chance to learn the liberal arts." Reflecting in a 1987 interview on the changes his profession has seen, he marveled at the advances in knowledge brought to the field. Yet he lamented that the art of medicine seemed to be on the decline. Instead, "What we have today is a group of highly-trained, efficient scientist with developed dexterity that are using ancillary materials, such as instruments and machines, far above their senses. The result is scientists who sell their knowledge and skill to customers who are buying care for their bodies." Doctors know very little in this day and age of going into the home to care for a patient. Dr. Nordlinger was a founder and past president of the Jacobi Society, member of the Washington Gynecological Society, and a member of the Society of the Emeriti of GW. His brother Bernard I. Nordlinger (B.A. 1929, J.D. 1933) won a Distinguished Alumni Award from GW in 1965. He and his wife Rosalie were married for fifty-four years, and had a daughter, Joan, born in 1932. Dr. Nordlinger died January 4, 1994 in Washington, D.C.
    This item was donated to the University Archives by Dr. Nordlinger's daughter Joan Nordlinger in 2003. An oral history was done with Dr. Nordlinger in 1991, and can be found in MS0371, the Oral History Collection. Formerly ACC#1052.
  - Postcards, photographs, Hatchet ID card, and clippings from Don Balfour, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Don Balfour is a 1948 graduate of The George Washington University with an Associates of Arts (AA) degree from the Columbian School of Arts and Sciences. The following year (1945) he earned a Bachelors degree (BA) from the School of Public and International Affix. While attending the university, Mr. Balfour worked as a reporter and later editor of the GW Hatchet. He was also active with the University Glee Club and Cue and Curtin (drama).
    Don Balfour interviewed the new commissioner for the GI Bill while serving as editor for the GW Hatchet. At the meeting he signed up for the GI Bill (having served in the U.S. Army) and thus became the first recipient of the GI Bill in the United States. Mr. Balfour donated his materials from his Hatchet days and information on the first GI Bill to the University Archives.
    Items include postcards of different campus buildings, the Houdon Statue, photographs of Cue and Curtain, the GW Hatchet Staff and his GW Hatchet card, Veteran's Club and University Glee Club members, two newspaper articles regarding GW veterans and one negative. Formerly Acc 691.
    An oral history done with Mr. Balfour can be found in MS0371, the Oral History Collection.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    Formerly Acc 691. Don Balfour is a 1948 graduate of The George Washington University with an Associates of Arts (AA) degree from the Columbian School of Arts and Sciences. The following year (1945) he earned a Bachelors degree (BA) from the School of Public and International Affix. While attending the university, Mr. Balfour worked as a reporter and later editor of the GW Hatchet. He was also active with the University Glee Club and Cue and Curtin (drama).
  - Photograph of Dr. Paul Adkins, 1972 ca. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    This photograph of Dr. Paul Adkins in surgery was taken by Alexander Hauptman who was a graduate of the class of 1973. The photo dates circa 1972. Formerly Acc#622.
  - Mrs. Fales photograph of the National University Medical School, class of 1900, 1900 -1961 -- --ca. (Flat box 29, Folder 1)
    This item consists of one large photograph of the 1900 National University Medical School class, which has an accompanying reprint and negative. Additionally, there is a four page handwritten, but unsigned letter from ca.1961. A donor noted only as "Mrs. Fales" gave a photograph of the 1900 National University Medical School to University Archives in 1995. There is no more information on her or the donation. The letter is assumed to written by a woman. She wrote about how she graduated from the Medical School at the National University in 1900, although there is no listing for her in the alumni directory. The letter details her and her husband's life and careers in the Washington, D.C. medical profession. Formerly Acc#346.
  - GW football squad, 1923 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    Francis Brown earned A.B (1924), LL.B. (1926), and LL.M. (1927) degrees from George Washington University. He later worked as the Attorney Examiner, Bureau of Air Mail, Interstate Commerce Commission. This material includes a photo of the GW football squad (1923) pictured on playing field where Jefferson Memorial now is. From left to right, the players are: Back Row: Coach Bill Quigley, Earl Manson, Jim Ptak, Allen, unknown, Hanes Pryor, unknown, unknown, unknown,; Second Row: Red Wallace, Kenaoski, Bart Codrin, Dave Stothin, Murphy, Francis Brown, unknown, unknown, unknown; Front Row: Unknown, Leeby, Stein, unknown, Guy Hottel, Dale Fisher, unknown, unknown. Mr. Brown donated the materials to University Archives in 1991. Formerly ACC#164.
  - Theta Delta Chi [members] before chapter house on N Street, 1920 ca. (Box 31, Folder 1)
    Francis Brown earned A.B (1924), LL.B. (1926), and LL.M. (1927) degrees from George Washington University. He later worked as the Attorney Examiner, Bureau of Air Mail, Interstate Commerce Commission. This material includes a photo of Theta Delta Chi before chapter house on N. Street, N.W. From left to right, the members iclude: Front Row: Ernest Henry (retired Attorney)Arthur Lerner (d); Second Row: William Herison (d), William Thomas (d), Russell Mason (d, GW Librarian), unknown Vernar Brown (d); Third Row: Unknown, Dale Fisher (d, Sir Force Col.), Francis Brown; Top Row: Charles Pledga (retired attorney), Carrol Meigs (d), Bogard Lifield (d), Dr. R. Miller (d), Eugene Thereas (d), Edaika Loemfle (d), unknown. Mr. Brown donated the materials to University Archives in 1991. Formerly ACC#164.
  - Theta Delta Chi Inter-fraternity championship team, 1925 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    Francis Brown earned A.B (1924), LL.B. (1926), and LL.M. (1927) degrees from George Washington University. He later worked as the Attorney Examiner, Bureau of Air Mail, Interstate Commerce Commission. This material includes a photo of Theta Delta Chi Inter-fraternity championship team of 1925. From left to right, the players are: Back Row: Cuttua Berna, Francis Brown (coach), Charles Pledger; Front Row: Dale Fisher, Jack Roberts, Liord Beeton, Elliott Bunnbough, Hal Bartlett. Mr. Brown donated the materials to University Archives in 1991. Formerly ACC#164.
  - Theta Delta Chi Letterman, 1925 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    Francis Brown earned A.B (1924), LL.B. (1926), and LL.M. (1927) degrees from George Washington University. He later worked as the Attorney Examiner, Bureau of Air Mail, Interstate Commerce Commission. This material includes a photo of Theta Delta Chi Letterman (1925). From left to right, the players are: William Thomas (football), Francis Brown (basketball), Beveridge (Bevs) Miller (football), and Dale Fisher (football). Mr. Brown donated the materials to University Archives in 1991. Formerly ACC#164.
  - Award of Hall of Fame from President Carroll to Francis Brown and Guy Hottel., 1964 ca. (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Francis Brown earned A.B (1924), LL.B. (1926), and LL.M. (1927) degrees from George Washington University. He later worked as the Attorney Examiner, Bureau of Air Mail, Interstate Commerce Commission. This material includes a photo of Francis Brown and Guy Hottel receiving GW Hall of Fame award from President Carroll. Mr. Brown donated the materials to University Archives in 1991. Formerly ACC#164.
  - 50th anniversary reunion Law School class of 1929, 05/11/1979 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    Francis Brown earned A.B (1924), LL.B. (1926), and LL.M. (1927) degrees from George Washington University. He later worked as the Attorney Examiner, Bureau of Air Mail, Interstate Commerce Commission. This material includes a photo of 50th anniversary reunion Law School class of 1929. Front row (left to right): Victor Dodge, LL.B. '23; Frank C. Sakran, JD '18; Theodore Sako, LL.B '29; Walter E. Nichols, LL.B '23; Harold Steve Blackman, LL.B '29; A. Everette MacIntyre, JD '29; Luis Padilla-Nervo, JD '29; John Damien Murphy, JD '29; Walter H. Zeydel, LL.B '29; Clifford A. Dougherty, JD '64, Director Law Alumni Relations; Back Row (left to right): Dean Robert Kramer, Leroy S. Bendheim, LL.B '29; Edgar P.Allen, LL.B'27, LL.M '35; Francis W. Brown, LL.B '26; Charles V. Laughlin, LL.B '29; Irving B. Yochelson, JD '29; Harold E. Luber, LL.B '28; Albert F. Adams, LL.B '29; Chalmers B. Yarley, LL. B, '29; Armand W. BeBirney, LL.B '29, John L. McCrea, JD '29; President Lloyd H. Elliott; Vincent P. Russo, LL.B '29. Mr. Brown donated the materials to University Archives in 1991. Formerly ACC#164.
  - GW varsity basketball team, 1924-1925 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    Francis Brown earned A.B (1924), LL.B. (1926), and LL.M. (1927) degrees from George Washington University. He later worked as the Attorney Examiner, Bureau of Air Mail, Interstate Commerce Commission. This material includes a photo of the GW varsity basketball team (1924-1925). From left to right: Back Row: Goldstein, Francis Brown, Ed Bettlalaim (mgr), Babe Hyde; Front Row: Otto Klopsk, Jack Dailey, Clarence (Guds) Gosnell. Mr. Brown donated the materials to University Archives in 1991. Formerly ACC#164.
  - Large group at table with cadaver, undated (Box 38, Folder 1.1)
  - Large group outside building, undated (Box 38, Folder 1.2)
  - Small group of students around table with cadaver (4 copies), undated (Box 38, Folder 1.3)
  - Washington Star Pictorial Magazine for June 14, 1953 (with photocopy of article on Dr. George W. Calver), 06/14/1953 (Box 38, Folder 1.4)
  - Herb "Mad Dog" Reeves cartoon, Circa 1930; Series 1 (Box 41, Folder data_value_missing_87c86207eef255b8ecab5befa8e39072)
    General
    Part of accession 2011.057. Henry Herbert Reeves played football and baseball at GW in the mid-1930s. He was a teacher and coach in Arkansas before enlisting in the Air Force and becoming a pilot. During World War II he served as an instructor of pilots. He retired after 31 years in the Air Force as a full Colonel. He died in 2007 at the age of 92. During his junior year at GW, Reeves was bit by a dog that was possibly rabid. He was given the nickname "Mad Dog" by his teammates. Cartoonist James Berryman drew this cartoon about Reeves and made reference to his Mad Dog nickname.
  - Edward Bagby images, 1860 (Box 45)
    Biographical / Historical
    Edward Bagby (1842-1864). In 1860-61 Edward Bagby was in his Junior year at Columbian College. In the spring of 1861, likely after Virginia's secession in April, several students moved to place a Confederate flag atop the College Building's cupola. Edward Bagby, age 19, from King and Queen County, Virginia, tried to convince his fellow southerners (perhaps even his own nephew, only 1 year younger, who was also a Junior) that this action would be imprudent. Failing that, he escorted President Samson to the cupola to remove it. The respect students gave him apparently helped protect the president from any harassment during this little crisis. Edward then left college to join the Virginia 36th Infantry, Company K. He was killed at the Battle of the Crater, outside Petersburg, July 30, 1864.
    Scope and Contents
    Print image and cased image, most likely a tintype, of Edward Bagby.
  - Class of 1970 sign, Series 1 (Box 46)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Donated by a CCAS class of 1970 member.
    This sign was outside welcoming new students to campus.
- Textiles and apparel, 1888-1961; MS2130 Series 2; 4 Linear feet (Flat box 14, Box 3, Box 1, Box 6)
  This collection includes football memorabilia and scrapbooks dating from 1888 to 1961. This series includes football blankets, sweaters, and an autographed football. The material also covers World War II.
  - Leather football cleats, 1950 ca. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Leather football cleats belonging to Thomas Flyzik who played for the George Washington University football team in the early 1950s.
    This collection was given to Special Collections in 1994 by Betty Flyzik. It contains memorabilia of her husband Thomas Flyzik, Class of 1953 and related to has activities while playing football for the university. The football program at GW lasted from 1908 to 1966.
    This note was written in 2005. Formerly Acc 231.
  - Football sweater, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Cream football sweater with '1953' patch stitched on front. This sweater belonged to Thomas Flyzik who played for the George Washington University football team in the early 1950s. His name is stitched inside the collar.
  - Autographed football, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Autographed football from the George Washington University's 1952 team. The football reads: " GW 21; Bucknell 7; '19' '52'; Bob Gutt; Steve Korcheck; George Semkew; Jack B_; John 'Pogo' Prach; Dick _; Hugo 'Val' Valdesiri; Jim 'Leon' England; Curly Kirchner; John 'the Greatest' _; Dick Geisler; Cecil 'Perky' Perkins; D Waldron; Frank Contenetti; Pat _; Leroy Courtney; Harry _; John Yedneck.
  - Football blanket, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Athletic blanket that belonged to Thomas Flyzik who played for the George Washington University football team in the late1940s and early 1950s. This blue blanket includes the GWU crest, GW letters, T. S. Flyzik name, and the years "1949-50-51-52" stitched into the fabric.
    This note was written in 2005. Donated by Betty Flyzik in 1994. Formerly Acc 231.
  - Athletic contact lenses, 1952 ca. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Small protective case with two plastic contact lenses inside, and a small cone shaped object. These lenses belonged to Thomas Flyzik who played football for George Washington University between the years 1949-1952.
  - Autographed football, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Autographed football from the GW vs. Wake Forest game, 1934. It is signed by: Hank Strayer, Ben Plotnick, 'Tuffy' Leemans, Frank Kavalier, George Trinascich, Torri Privot (?), Charles Mann, Hank Vander Brugge, Ed Clark, Ray Hanken, George Jenkins, Bernie Witucki, Benny Benefield, Ed, Horace Pettit, Joe Glick, Pete Lind, Dean Alexander, Dale Prather, Pete Breazeal, and 1 other illegible name.
    Francis Strayer presented these materials to the university in October of 1993. Strayer was a 1934 graduate of the university, playing both football and baseball for GW. This note was written in 2005.
    Formerly Acc 203.
  - Athletic blanket, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    George Washington University (GWU) athletic blanket. It is embroidered with the GWU crest, the year 1934, and the name"Henry Strayer".
    Francis Henry Strayer presented these materials to the University in October of 1993. Strayer was a 1934 graduate of the University, playing both football and baseball for GW. This note was written in 2005.
  - Athletic sweater, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    George Washington University athletic sweater (possibly a letterman sweater) from 1934. This sweater is cream with the letters G and W embroidered on the front.
  - Mess hat, 1956 ca. --1961 -- --ca. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    This mess hat, constructed with a paper base and a mesh cap, was worn by Ann Sneeringer McKay when she served Christmas dinner at the mess hall. Ann McKay was a member of The George Washington University Cheerleading Team during the late 1950s. She received her B.A. in Education from GW in 1960. She was also active in the Glee Club, Traveling Troubadours, and Student Council. This note was written in 2005.
    Donated by Ann Marie Sneeringer McKay. Formerly Acc 471
  - Letterman sweater, 1924 ca. (Flat box 14, Folder 1)
    Letterman sweater, with "GW" on the front, worn by Francis Brown, ca.1924. Brown earned an A.B. 1924; LL.B. 1926; and LL.M. 1927 from George Washington University. Formerly ACC#164.
  - Kerchief, 1888 (Flat box 14, Folder 2)
    Red and white kerchief for the campaign of President Grover Cleveland and Vice-President candidate Allen G. Thurman, 1888. Has slogans "Tariff reform for revenue only," "No surplus," "Low taxes," and "Public office a public trust" written on it. Belonged to George C. Samson. Samson was the son of Columbian College President George W. Samson, and he earned and A.B. in 1865, an M.D. in 1867, and an A.M. in 1868 from the college. He was later in charge of the Soldiers' and Sailors' Orphan Home, Washington, D.C., 1870-79; served on the Board of Trustees for the Public Schools of the District of Columbia, 1878-82; served as a Board Manager for the YMCA, Washington D.C., 1891-97; served as a Board Manager for the Washington City Bible Society, 1888-99; served as Treasurer of the Baptist Social Union, District of Columbia, 1898-99; and was a member of the Medical Society of the District of Columbia. Formerly ACC#964.
  - Cap and gown of Dr. George Nordlinger, 1925 ca. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Blanket, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Item 3)
    This blanket was part of accession 2011.057. Henry Herbert Reeves owned this blanket. He played football and baseball at GW in the mid-1930s. He was a teacher and coach in Arkansas before enlisting in the Air Force and becoming a pilot. During World War II he served as an instructor of pilots. He retired after 31 years in the Air Force as a full Colonel. He died in 2007 at the age of 92.
- Scrapbooks, 1925-1933; MS2130 Series 3; 3..5 Linear Feet Two oversize boxes (Box 36, Box 9, Box 16, Box 25, Box 8, Flat box 33)
  This collection contains scrapbooks, photographs, and correspondence. They range in date from 1927 to 1993.
  The material consists of photographs of GW professors and scrapbooks about football.
  - Francis Strayer football scrapbook, 1927 -1993 -- --ca. (Box 6, Folder 7)